Inventory of the Martin Papers 1862-1868
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Martin Papers, 1862-1868.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.2 M36
43 items.
Inventory includes papers, 1862-1868, of the Martin family of North Carolina, chiefly the correspondence of Major Thomas Alston Martin who served in the 13th North Carolina Infantry. Includes letters, 1862, of R. C. Martin written while serving in the Confederate Army. Many letters in the collection are written by women.
Martin Family.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Biographical/Historical Information
Thomas A Martin was from Franklin County, North Carolina. He enlisted as a Corporal in Co. E., 13th N. C. May 9, 1861. He served as a sergeant, Lt. and Capt. He was wounded in the hip at Gettysburg and was promoted to major January 19, 1865. Martin was paroled at Appomattox. [Source: Kirk, Robert K., Lee's Colonels: a biographical register of the Field Officers of the Army of Northern Virginia. Dayton, Ohio: Press of Morningside Bookshop, 1979]
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains papers of the Martin family of North Carolina. It is primarily composed of papers and correspondence with relatives in North Carolina and Virginia, 1862-1868, belonging to Major Thomas Alston Martin who served in the 13th North Carolina Infantry. Several letters date to the Civil War and refer to camp conditions. It includes letters, 1862, of R. C. Martin written while serving in the Confederate Army. Many of the letters were written by women.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 2 series. Series 1 contains letters and series 2 contains miscellaneous items.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in chronological order by the dates on the letters.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Confederate States of America. Army. North Carolina Infantry Regiment, 13th.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Contents List
  Series 1: Letters
- Letters, 1862-1868.
  - R.C. Martin, Yorktown, Virginia, to his sister Vic [?], 23 February 1862., 1 page. ALS.
  - R. C. Martin, Goldsborough [sic], [North Carolina], to his sister Vic [?], 30 March 1862., 1 page. ALS.
  - T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], Camp Ruffin, Virginia, to his sister [?], 30 March 1862., 2 pages. ALS.
  - T[homas] A[lston] Martin, near Richmond, Virginia, to his sister [?], 20 May 1862., 2 pages. ALS.
  - R. C. Martin, Richmond, [Virginia], to his sister [?], 7 June 1862., 2 pages. ALS.
  - T[homas] Alston Martin, near Richmond, Virginia, to his sister [?], 13 June 1862., 2 pages. ALS.
  - Vic [?], to her brother Thomas [Alston Martin], n.p., 2 February 1863., 2 pages. ALS.
  - T[homas] Alston Martin, Camp Gregg, Virginia, to his sister [?], 19 February [18]63., 2 pages. ALS.
  - Lou [?], to her cousin [?], 5 January 1864., 2 pages. ALS.
  - J.B. Boson[?], in Camp near Orange C[ourt] H[ouse], Virginia, to Capt. Thomas A[lston] Martin, n.p., 13 February 1864., 2 pages. ALS.
  - J. Rich[ard] Ireland, Greensboro, North Carolina, to T[h]om[as] A[lston] Martin, n.p., 23 February 1864., 2 pages. ALS.
  - Sarah [?], to her brother [?], 24 April 1864., 2 pages. ALS.
  - Vic [?], Wilmington, [North Carolina], to her brother [?], April 1864., 4 pages. ALS.
  - Thomas W. [Fawtt?], Danville, Virginia, to Thomas [Alston] Martin, n.p., 23 September 1864., 2 pages. ALS.
  - Lupus [Eliza Crenshaw], Cheraw, South Carolina, to her cousin T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p., 5 December 1864., 4 pages. ALS.
    Enclosure: a calling card.
  - Maddie [Crenshaw], to her cousin T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p., 2 January 1865., 3 pages. ALS.
  - J. Rich[ard] Ireland, Kinston, North Carolina, to T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p., 29 January 1866., 4 pages. ALS.
  - Buck Bowly, Bowling Green, to T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p., 18 April 1866., 4 pages. ALS.
  - Lizzie W. Crenshaw, Statesville, North Carolina, T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p., 10 August 1866., 3 pages. ALS.
  - Martin & Tannahill, Petersburg, Virginia, to W.K. Martin, Pacific, Franklin County, North Carolina PM, 29 September 1866., 1 page.
  - W.S. Long, Graham, [North Carolina], to W.K. Martin, n.p., 26 November 1866., 4 pages. ALS.
  - Lucie [?], Oxford, North Carolina to her cousin T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p., 9 February 1868., 4 pages. ALS.
  - Lucie [?], Oxford, North Carolina, to her cousin T[h]om[as][Alston Martin], n.p., 17 March 1868., 4 pages. ALS.
  - Lucie [?], Oxford, North Carolina, to her cousin T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p., 6 April 1868., 4 pages. ALS.
  - Lucie [?], Oxford, North Carolina, to her cousin T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p., 16 April 1868., 4 pages. ALS.
  - Lucie [?], Hickory Grove, [Prince William County Virginia], to T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p., 29 May 1868., 4 pages. ALS.
  - M.A. Cox, Goldsboro, North Carolina, to Maj. [Thomas Alston] Martin, n.p., 4 June 1868., 2 pages. ALS.
  - Mcllwaine & Co., Petersburg, Virginia, to Maj. T[homas] A[lston] Martin, Forestville, North Carolina, 25 June 1868., 1 page. ALS.
  - Mcllwaine & Co., Petersburg, Virginia, to Maj. T[homas] A[lston] Martin, Forestville, North Carolina, 7 July 1868., 1 page. ALS.
  - Robert A. Martin & Co., Petersburg, Virginia, to Maj T[homas] A[lston] Martin, Forestville, North Carolina, 5 October 1868., 1 page. PM.
  Series 2: Miscellaneous
- Miscellaneous 1862-1868.
  - Invoices, receipts, and tax bills of T[homas] A[lston] Martin, 1868., 7 items.
  - [?] to Mr. Martin, 11 October 18[?].
  - D.G. Crenshaw, Falkland, [North Carolina], to his cousin T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p., 29 May n.y., 5 pages. ALS.
  - D.G. Crenshaw, Falkland, [North Carolina], to his cousin T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p. Incomplete, 29 June n.y., 2 pages. ALS.
  - [D.C. Crenshaw], n.p., to his cousin T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p. Incomplete, n.d., 2 pages. AL.
  - Vic [?], to her sister Sal [?], n.d., 4 pages. ALS.
  - Vic [?], to her brother T[h]om[as] [Alston Martin], n.p., n.d., 2 pages. ALS.